<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>jprocha</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on jprocha</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 10:30:35 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>RAG for Scientists and Science Students</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/til/rag_for_science_and_students/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 10:30:35 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/til/rag_for_science_and_students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I&amp;rsquo;ve saw the internet be flooded with the term &lt;strong&gt;RAG&lt;/strong&gt;, which&#xA;stands for &lt;em&gt;Retrieval Augmented Generation&lt;/em&gt;. At the time i didn&amp;rsquo;t paid a lot of&#xA;attention, since it was related with the much hyped subject of Generative AI&#xA;and LLMs (Large Language Models), so I&amp;rsquo;ve thought it wasn&amp;rsquo;t that useful and&#xA;people was talking about it just because it was aligned with the hype cycle.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, yesterday I&amp;rsquo;ve took a look at it &amp;hellip; And discovered that i was&#xA;wrong, this thing is highly useful (specially for ADHD people like myself).&#xA;After some time reflecting about my attitude of judging the book by it&amp;rsquo;s cover,&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ve researched a bit about more the subject and started to think about the&#xA;possibilities (i&amp;rsquo;ll leave the resources i&amp;rsquo;ve found useful at the bottom). I&amp;rsquo;ll now&#xA;share with you the core idea of it and then some i&amp;rsquo;ve had that i think will be&#xA;useful for scientist and science students (like me). I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on RAGs&#xA;for text data, still, it can be used with other types of media, the idea is&#xA;roughly the same, with some asterisks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flying Cows</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/til/flying_cows/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 20:51:36 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/til/flying_cows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The physics of flying cows is a really interesting subject, which is&#xA;very important for the economy, given that their poop can fertilize&#xA;entire fields in an efficient air bone manner.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless they can also be a problem when flying cows flyes over&#xA;cities, since they can fall on business places growing the business&#xA;expenses on poop cleaning, given that they already have their own to&#xA;clean, this process is quite inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m João Pedro Rocha, a Graduate Student in Scientific Computing at LNCC&#xA;(National Laboratory for Scientific Computing, &amp;#x1f1e7;&amp;#x1f1f7;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m from a Physics background and am now developing research in Scientific&#xA;Machine Learning, with Physics Informed Neural Networks applied to Transport&#xA;Phenomena for nuclear reactor safety.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also do some work with Astrophysical data processing, mainly photometrical&#xA;time series, acquired with the telescopes managed by the LNA (National Astrophysics&#xA;Laboratory, also &amp;#x1f1e7;&amp;#x1f1f7;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
